Finding Aid for News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Audiovisual Materials
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Video Materials
  - Science Lectures, 1992-2005
    The Science Lectures sub-series consists of 17 tapes in the DVCam, VHS, U-Matic, and Betacam formats dated between 1992 and 2005 featuring lectures by UM scholars and visiting lectures on subjects related to Physics, the Environment, and Biology.
    - TLE Movie, Original Remediation, Insitu Air Stripping, [Undated]., Betacam Tape (Box 13)
    - 3D Animations of Ground Water Contamination, Institute of Water Research & Development, MSU, October, 1992, Betacam Tape (Box 13)
    - National Association of Conservation Districts "Clean Water, Clear Choices", July 17, 1991, Betacam Tape (Box 13)
    - UM School of Natural Resources, HSRC, February 18, 1991, U-Matic Tape (Box 13)
    - UM School of Natural Resources, HSRC, February 18, 1991, U-Matic Tape (Box 13)
    - UM School of Natural Resources: Waste Minimization Module, December 1991, Betacam Tape (Box 13)
    - UM School of Natural Resources Doe Cercla Site Assessment, 1994, Betacam Tape (Box 13)
    - "The Earth's Changing Atmosphere," Arthur F. Thurnau Professor and Professor of Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences Perry Samson, January 26, 2002, VHS Tape (Box 13)
    - AOSS "The Sun's Changing Atmosphere" Professor Leonard Fisk, February 2, 2002, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - Stephen Wolfram, "A New Kind of Science", October 8, 2002, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - Life Style of a Galaxy in an Accelerating Universe, December 7, 2002, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - From Imes to Moore I, March 17, 2004, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - From Imes to Moore II, March 17, 2004 UM 22 Edit, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - Global Warming, Fossil Fuels, and the Audacity of Imagining We Can Shape Our Energy Future, September 28, 2004 Michigan TV 2 Edit, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - The Public Perception of Genes, Maxine Singer, October 20, 2004, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - Risk Science; John D. Graham, John H. Marburger III, September 15-16, 2005, DVCam Tape (Box 13)
    - Science Abled Good Minds at Work, [Undated], VHS Tape
  - Statements and Media Events with University Presidents, 1982-2005
    The Statements and Media Events on University Presidents sub-series consists of 32 video tapes of mixed formats: U-matic, VHS, Betacam, and DVCam tape. These tapes, with dates ranging from 1982 to 2003, document the media appearances of various University Presidents from Harold Shapiro to Mary Sue Coleman. The content of the tapes includes University Presidential inaugurations, State of the University addresses, and media materials produced for alumni and the larger UM community that explicitly features a President of the University.
    - UM President Harold Shapiro and UCLA Chancellor Charles Young on NBC-TV's "Today" December 28, 1982, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - Regional TV coverage of James Duderstadt being named UM president: WXYZ-TV, WDIV-TV, WKBD-TV. June 10, 1988, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - PRES; Edited JJD Inauguration with Rose Bowl Scenes, 1989, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - Regional TV coverage of James Duderstadt being named UM president: WXYZ-TV, WDIV-TV, WKBD-TV; followed by UM Biomedical Communications' recording of the Regents meeting, June 10, 1988, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - UM President James Duderstadt's 1988 State of the University Address, 1988, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - Regional TV coverage of James Duderstadt's first State of the University address: WDIV-TV, WXYZ-TV, Detroit. October 3, 1988, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - Regional TV coverage of the inauguration of UM President James Duderstadt: WXYZ-TV, WDIV-TV, WJRT-TV, Detroit; WILX-TV, Lansing/Jackson; WNEM-TV, Saginaw, October 6-7, 1988, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - UM President James Duderstadt outlines the Michigan Mandate at the Renaissance Center in Detroit, November 10, 1988, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - President Duderstadt in a one-hour satellite broadcast to alumni groups around the nation, originating in the Presidents house, April 9,1989, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - UM President James Duderstadt outlining the Michigan Mandate for new student orientation, April 27, 1989, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - UM President James Duderstadt at a news conference announcing the Campaign for Michigan, 1991, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - "A Conversation with University Leaders," produced by WFUM-TV, January, 1992, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - "A Conversation with President Duderstadt: Graduate Education," with Rackham Graduate School Dean John D'Arms and five graduate students produced by WFUM-TV, 1992-1993, Betacam Tape [two tapes], VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - "An Afternoon with the Presidents" is a discussion before an audience in Power Center of their UM experiences by President James Duderstadt and former UM presidents Robben Fleming, Harlan Hatcher and Harold Shapiro and former acting president Allen Smith, November 10, 1992, U-Matic Tape [two tapes] (Box 12)
    - "Michigan at Risk: Higher Education" with a panel of university presidents---James Duderstadt (University of Michigan), M. Peter McPherson (Michigan State University), Davad Adamany (Wayne State University) and Arend D. Lubbers (Grand Valley State University). Produced by Michigan Public Broadcasting, February 1994, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - UM President James Duderstadt outlining the Michigan Agenda for Women at a Warner Lambert-Parke Davis seminar, March 6, 1995, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - WXYZ-TV's "Spotlight on the News" is an interview with UM President James Duderstadt, November 12, 1995, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - Inauguration of Lee Bollinger as UM president, September 19, 1997, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - Inauguration of Lee Bollinger as UM president, September 19, 1997, U-Matic Tape (Box 12)
    - ESPN's "Outside the Lines" segment with former UM President James Duderstadt discussing college sports, January 1, 2001, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - Television coverage of Mary Sue Coleman announcing she would leave the University of Iowa for the University of Michigan, April 29-30, 2002, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - Regents meeting at which Mary Sue Coleman was named UM president, May 29, 2002, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - Mary Sue Coleman Address, September 26, 2002 MiTV2 Edit, DVCam Tape (Box 12)
    - Implications of Expanding Concepts of Literacy in Higher Education; UM President's Panel, October 4, 2002 UMTV 22 Edit, DVCam Tape (Box 12)
    - President Mary Sue Coleman Addresses Senate Assembly, October 13, 2002 UMTV 22 Edit, DVCam Tape (Box 12)
    - Regent Candidates Forum October 14, 2002 UMTV 22 Edit, DVCam Tape (Box 12)
    - Mary Sue Coleman addresses the American Council on Education via satellite from the Ann Arbor campus, February 17, 2003, VHS Tape (Box 12)
    - For the University of the World; Inauguration Symposium; March 27, 2003 UMTV 22 Edit, DVCam Tape (Box 12)
    - State of the Universities Address, November 12, 2003 UM 22 Badged, DVCam Tape (Box 12)
    - Mary Sue Coleman's Future Directions, April 22, 2004 Arthur Greene Concert, December 4, 2003, DVCam Tape (Box 12)
    - President Mary Sue Coleman's Address, September 20, 2004, DVCam Tape
  - University Orientation Video, 1989-1999
    The University Orientation Video sub-series consists of 25 VHS, DVCam, Betacam and U-Matic tapes dated from 1998 to 1999. These tapes depict UM campus shots and orientation videos for new students. Of note is a video orienting students on how to use the University of Michigan's Computer Showcase.
    - Student Orientation Video Rough cut Kris Korzecke, April 27, 1992, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation Video, April 30, 1992, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation Video, September 29, 1989, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation Video Rough cut Andre McKoy, April 17, 1992, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation Video Rough cut Brooke Lutz, April 27, 1992, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Orientation I, Undated, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation Video, May 20, 1992, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - U of M Orientation, interview with Jason Harrison, August 6, 1992, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation, September 29, 1989, U-Matic Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation, October 16, 1989, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Orientation 1987 May 19, 1987, VHS Tape (Box 26)
    - Student Orientation, August 2-3, 1989, U-Matic Tape (Box 26)
    - Orientation 1998 Campus Shots, Tom Sims, Erik Olsen, April 24, 1998, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Orientation 1998 Ethernet Summit, May 6, 1998, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Orientation 1998 Ethernet Summit, May 6, 1998, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Orientation Rough Footage, Tom Sims, Erik Olsen, Tape 1, July 31, 1998, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Orientation Rough Footage, Tom Sims, Erik Olsen, Tape 2, July 31, 1998, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Pete's Great Adventure, 1998 Orientation, August 10, 1998, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Computer Showcase Orientation, 99, May 3, 1999, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Orientation 1999 May 4, 1999, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Orientation 1999 May 5, 1999, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Orientation Open and Close, Master Footage, July 21, 1999, Betacam Tape (Box 15)
    - Consider Michigan! [Undated], VHS Tape (Box 15)
    - Discover the Michigan Advantage, [Undated], VHS Tape (Box 15)
    - UM Freshmen Program; [Undated], DVCam Tape
  - University of Michigan Solar Car Events,1990-1993
    The UM Solar Car sub-series consists of 11 tapes of mixed video formats: U-matic, Betacam, and VHS tapes, documenting the media appearances of the University of Michigan's Solar Car project from 1990 to 1993. Included are the Solar Car's appearances at the Sunrunner and Sunrayce solar car events as well as related media coverage on the car and its development at the University of Michigan.
    - Sunrunner UM solar car unveiling, Sunrayce start at Disneyworld, solar cars on the road during race and Sunrunner arriving at race finish line in Warren, Michigan, 1990, U-Matic Tape (Box 14)
    - Sunrunner UM solar car unveiling, 1990, Betacam Tape (Box 14)
    - Sunrunner UM solar car tests at Michigan International Speedway, June 6, 1990, U-Matic Tape (Box 14)
    - Detroit TV coverage of end of Sunrayce: WJBK-TV, WDIV-TV and WXYZ-TV. July 19, 1990, U-Matic Tape (Box 14)
    - Sunrunner UM solar car, July 1990, U-Matic Tape [two tapes] (Box 14)
    - Top three Sunrayce solar car finishers, 1990, U-Matic Tape (Box 14)
    - Impact Environmental Reports: Two reports by the UM Solar Car Team, February 3, 1992 (Box 14)
    - UM solar car promo tape, 1993, VHS Tape (Box 14)
    - UM solar car and two other solar cars competing in Sunrayce 93, Summer 1993, U-Matic Tape (Box 14)
    - UM solar car and two other solar cars competing in Sunrayce 93, Copies were distributed to regional TV stations, Summer 1993, Betacam Tape (Box 14)
    - URegional TV coverage of the Maize and Blue UM solar car in Sunrayce 1993 WJBK-TV, WXYZ-TV, WDIV-TV, WKBD-TV (Detroit); WWMT-TV (Kalamazoo/Grand Rapids), June 20-28, 1993, U-Matic Tape (Box 14)
  - Wolverine Sports Magazine, 2000-2006
    The Wolverine Sports Magazine sub-series features 15 DVCam tapes with dates ranging from approximately 1990 to 2006. Wolverine Sports Magazine was broadcast on the UMTV Channel 22 until eventually moving into an exclusively online format in the late 2000s.
    - Features for the Sports Television series "Wolverine Sports Magazine", [between 1990 and 2000], DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2003-2004 II, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2003-2004 III, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2003-2004 IV, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2003-2004 V, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2003-2004 VI, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2004-2005 I, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2004-2005 II, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2004-2005 IV, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2004-2005 V, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2004-2005 V, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2004-2005 VI, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2005-2006 Raw I, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag 2005-2006 Edit I, DVCam Tape (Box 7)
    - The Mag: [Undated], DVCam Tape (Box 7)
- Audio Podcasts, 2006-2010
  The Audio Podcasts series contains audio podcasts produced by the News and Information Service starting in 2006. The podcasts were mainly disseminated through the News and Information Website, and primarily include stories about research and creative works by University of Michigan faculty. Other topics include the expansion of and events at the University of Michigan Museum of Art, the leadership vision of the University's president, and visiting speakers.
  The podcasts are now hosted as downloadable mp3 files in Deep Blue, the University of Michigan's institutional repository. The listing for each podcast includes the title, date of recording, the filename, length (in minutes and seconds), the mime-type of the file and, in most cases, an abstract of the podcast's content and the speakers. The podcasts are organized chronologically by date of recording or first release.
  - 2006
    - Keynote Address for the Professional and Scholarly Publishing Division of the Association of American Publishers 7/11/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman delivered the keynote opening address of the 2006 conference of the Professional and Scholarly Publishing Division of the Association of American Publishers in Washington, D.C., Feb. 6, 2006.
    - Inauguration, March 27, 2003 7/11/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman's remarks at her inauguration as the University of Michigan's 13th president.
    - President Mary Sue Coleman Speech at National Press Club 7/11/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman at the National Press Club in Washington, D.C., March 7, 2006.
    - President Mary Sue Coleman's Remarks to Graduates, 2005 Spring Commencement 7/11/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman's remarks to graduates at Spring Commencement, April 30 2005, in Michigan Stadium.
    - President Mary Sue Coleman's Remarks to Graduates, 2006 Spring Commencement 7/11/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman's remarks to graduates at Spring Commencement, April 29 2006, in Michigan Stadium.
    - President Mary Sue Coleman's Remarks to Graduates, 2004 Winter Commencement 7/11/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman's remarks to graduates at Winter Commencement, Dec. 19, 2004, in Michigan Stadium.
    - President Mary Sue Coleman's Remarks to Graduates, 2005 Winter Commencement 7/11/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman's remarks to graduates at Winter Commencement, Dec. 18, 2005, in Michigan Stadium.
    - Cell phone survey 7/13/2006, .mp3 file; Michael Traugott discusses a survey done about opinions on the public use of cell phones.
    - Targeting cancer stem cell 7/14/2006, .mp3 file; Cancer has rejuvenating stem cells, just like organs do. Sean Morrison's group has found a way to selectively identify and kill just the cancerous stem cells in mice with leukemia, leaving healthy blood-forming stem cells alone.
    - Women on TV 7/24/2006, .mp3 file; From "Xena: Warrior Princess" to "Judging Amy," television shows are redefining women in dramatic roles by telling diverse stories about their lives, a University of Michigan analysis shows.
    - Stock-Option Dating Games 7/28/2006, .mp3 file; U.S. executives engage in stock-option dating games to boost pay.
    - Tobacco and IQ 8/11/2006, .mp3 file; University of Michigan Research Assistant Prof. Jennifer Glass says her research indicates years of tobacco use may dim the speed and accuracy of a person's thinking ability and bring down their IQ.
    - Bone loss and menopause 8/18/2006, .mp3 file; Bone loss actually starts before estrogen and the decline of estrogen levels, probably because of another hormone's activity.
    - A gene for 'middle aged spread' 8/18/2006, .mp3 file; Stephen Weiss' research team was looking for a gene that affected the development of the circulatory system in mice. Quite by mistake, they found a 'molecular scissors' that loosens the collagen belt around fat cells, allowing them to expand.
    - Biology without a book 8/25/2006, .mp3 file; Professor Dan Klionsky in the Life Science Institute believes that students can learn biology without books or lectures.
    - Who helps the poor? 9/4/2006, .mp3 file; University of Michigan public policy Prof. Sheldon Danziger discusses latest poverty trends.
    - 9/11 five years later 9/10/2006, .mp3 file; University of Michigan history Prof. Juan Cole discusses whether or not we are winning the fight against al-Qaeda.
    - UMMA expands 9/18/2006, .mp3 file; University or Michigan Museum of Art (UMMA) Director James Steward discusses UMMA's expansion and renovation.
    - People Accounting 9/25/2006, .mp3 file; Research by UM psychologists suggests that people commonly consider social categories when making decisions about who to hire, etc.
    - Sparling on Graham 10/6/2006, .mp3 file; From 1973-1987 Sparling was a principal dancer with the Graham Company, having previously danced with the Jose Limon Dance Company.
    - The legacy of Gerald Ford 10/15/2006, .mp3 file; Steven and Susan Ford were on the University of Michigan campus for the dedication of the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy's new home, Joan and Sanford Weill Hall.
    - Scientific integrity 10/17/2006, .mp3 file; University of Michigan ecology and evolutionary biology Prof. Knute Nadelhoffer organized a Summit on Scientific Integrity at the U-M Biological Station in July 2006 that brought together researchers, politicians and citizens.
    - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Energy Institute 10/20/2006, .mp3 file; The University of Michigan is launching an interdisciplinary institute to increase the university's commitment to energy research.
    - Why are Americans so bad at math? 11/3/2006, .mp3 file; It's become common for Americans to laughingly say "oh well, I am no good at math so my child is not either." Could you imagine anyone saying those words about reading? Deborah Ball, a member of a White House panel on improving math instruction and dean of the U-M School of Education, talks about how Americans as a society got so far behind in math and what we need to do to get back to where we need to be. Why is it important to be proficient at math and how can we get there? Ball explains why.
    - Boys with Crucifixes - Poem by Ray McDaniel 11/3/2006., .mp3 file
    - Fever of the Divine - Poem by Ray McDaniel 11/3/2006., .mp3 file
    - Through the Shotgun House, with Violins - Poem by Ray McDaniel 11/3/2006, .mp3 file
    - Post-traumatic stress syndrome after disasters 11/3/2006, .mp3 file; In the year after a hurricane, tornado, terrorist attack or other natural or man-made disaster, 30-40 percent of adults who were directly affected may suffer from post-traumatic stress disorder.
    - International adoptions 11/3/2006., .mp3 file; Interest in international adoptions has grown tremendously within the last two decades.
    - Letter with No Address - Poem by Donald Hall 11/3/2006., .mp3 file
    - Striving toward perfection 11/3/2006, .mp3 file; President Mary Sue Coleman's address to University of Michigan Faculty Senate Assembly, October 30, 2006.
    - Blue Tips - Poem by Sean Norton 11/8/2006, .mp3 file
    - A Bowl Full of Pearls - Poem by Britta Ameel 06 MFA 11/8/2006, .mp3 file
    - After the Gallatin River, Outside Bozeman, Montana - Poem by Britta Ameel 06 MFA 11/8/2006, .mp3 file
    - December - Poem By Erin Morris 11/8/2006., .mp3 file
    - Umbilical Poem - Poem By Erin Morris 11/8/2006, .mp3 file
    - The potential of nuclear power as a clean energy option 11/27/2006, .mp3 file; Nuclear engineering and radiological sciences deals with the human application of subatomic particles with energies from fractions of an electron volt to millions of electron volt, and with the interactions of radiation with matter.
    - The evolution of sexual selection 12/13/2006, .mp3 file; Facial masculinity may serve as a visual cue in female mate choice, much as the tail of the male peacock signals females about male fitness to reproduce.
    - Composers' work inspiration for dance 12/13/2006, .mp3 file; Composers' work inspiration for dance performance that was be part of 2006-07 national tour.
  - 2007
    - Accreditation creates new steps for School of Dance 01/02/2007, .mp3 file; DeYoung says, "Through our teaching and key collaborations around the University, we've proven that the dance is perhaps the most agile of all art forms, drawing on many disciplines, from the visual arts to science."
    - Fortifying bridge from Ann Arbor to Detroit 1/8/2007, .mp3 file; Dec. 5 trip is up close look at potential impact of new site.
    - Smoking rates higher among low-income African-Americans 1/15/2007, .mp3 file; As overall smoking rates in the U.S. decline, the smoking rate among low-income African-Americans increases.
    - Poems by Roy Alan Jacobstein 1/18/2007, .mp3 file
    - Spanking isn't the only solution 01/22/2007, .mp3 file; Andrew Grogan-Kaylor says his new study indicates children who get high levels of intellectual stimulation at home, such as books and educational games, had parents who rarely used physical punishment.
    - Time, money and who does the laundry 1/30/2007, .mp3 file; Women and girls still spend more time than men and boys on housework.
    - Black History Month is still relevant today 2/2/2007, .mp3 file; Percy Bates says it's important for society, especially young people, to know about the history of other races. While it's great that one month focuses on the contributions of African-Americans, he would like to see black history -- as well as the history of other ethnic groups -- taught year round.
    - Nuclear power generates waste with special needs 2/12/2007, .mp3 file; Nuclear engineering and radiological science Prof. William Martin outlines research projects in nuclear energy at the U-M and discusses how nuclear waste is to be disposed in the U.S.
    - Not your father's addictions... (2/19/2007, .mp3 file; U-M Research Professor Lloyd Johnston compares today's teens with teens of 33 years ago and everyone in between. His Monitoring the Future survey has surveyed more than 1 million teens since the study began in 1975 asking them about drug use, smoking, drinking and other habits every year. A Distinguished Research Scientist at U-M's Institute for Social Research, Johnston is principal investigator of the Monitoring the Future study.
    - TV and chubby children 3/5/2007, .mp3 file; University of Michigan researchers found that 3-year-old children exposed to two or more hours of TV a day were nearly three times more likely to be overweight than children who either watched or were in a room with a TV on for fewer than two hours a day,.
    - Prisoner art exhibition 3/19/2007, .mp3 file; With participation and attendance increasing since the first exhibit 12 years ago, the Annual Exhibition of Art by Michigan Prisoners is making connections between prisoners and the community, and de-constructing stereotypes about those incarcerated.
    - Arthur Miller Theatre opening 3/26/2007, .mp3 file; University of Michigan professor Enoch Brater talks about playwright Arthur Miller as the University hosts a grand opening of the Arthur Miller Theatre, the only one in the world named after Miller.
    - Asymmetric journalism 4/2/2007, .mp3 file; McDonald is a veteran newspaper correspondent who has done several tours in Iraq and Afghanistan.
    - Are you High Testosterone and is that good? 4/9/2007, .mp3 file; U-M psychology professor Oliver Schultheiss, who runs the Human Motivation and Affective Neuroscience Lab, talks about how hormones like testosterone impact human behavior. Schultheiss describes how to tell if you're "high testosterone" and the pluses and minuses.